A Guide to the American Rhododendron Society Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-d, -e, and -f
American Rhododendron Society Papers 1931-1987
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-d, -e and -f
ca. 2800 items
Paula L. Cash, Harry L. Wise, and Sandra McDonald
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Any quotations from the records and volumes of the American Rhododendron Society (10,553-d-e) in any media must be approved in advance by the Society. The Records of the Middle Atlantic Chapter and Le-Mac Nurseries (10,553-f) are unrestricted. Contact Curator for details.
Acquisition Information
The American Rhododendron Society records and volumes (10,553-d-e) were given to the Library through Ms. Paula L. Cash, the Executive Secretary, of Tigard, Oregon, and Mr. Harry L. Wise of Charleston, West Virginia, on June 3, 1987. The Middle Atlantic Chapter Records and Le-Mac Nurseries Records were given to the Library by Dr. Sandra McDonald of Hampton, Virginia, on July 20, 1987.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 2,800 items (12 Hollinger boxes, 4 linear feet), 1931-1987, records of the American Rhododendron Society, the Middle Atlantic Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society, and Le-Mac Nurseries, Hampton, Virginia.
The American Rhododendron Society series contains correspondence, financial records, chapter-related materials, minutes of the National Board of Director's Meetings, records of the Awards and Publication Committees, membership lists, newsletters, and printed material.
The correspondence of the American Rhododendron Society includes that between various chapters and the national headquarters and the correspondence of several past national officers, such as Dr. J. Harold Clarke, Edward B. Dunn, Fred C. Galle, Ruth Hansen, August Kehr, A. S. Martin, Dr. Carl H. Phetteplace, George W. Ring, III, and Dr. Robert L. Ticknor.
Prominent topics in the first series include: the controversy concerning the transfer of Research and Education Funds to the Research Foundation Account, the International Rhododendron Conference (1961), National Conventions (1966-1971, & 1980), the Pacific Conference of 1970, the Pollen Bank, the Pukeiti Rhododendron Trust, the
Quarterly Bulletin
, the rhododendron rating project, the rhododendron species glossary, the seed exchange, and the test garden of the American Rhododendron Society in Portland, Oregon.
Series II consists of ten bound volumes of financial record books of the American Rhododendron Society, including a membership record book and an advertising record book.
The third series contains the records of the Middle Atlantic Chapter, chiefly the records of the Secretary-Treasurer, membership lists, and correspondence. The correspondence files include those of Kenneth McDonald, the Denmark Chapter, with political figures, the controversy over the transfer of Research and Education Funds to the Research Foundation Account, the formation of the Middle Atlantic Chapter, the Gold Medal nominations, and newsletter ideas.
The Le-Mac Nurseries Records comprise the fourth series. These papers consist of two folders concerning Azalea Flower Spot Disease ( Ovulinia Azaleae Weiss), and correspondence between Le-Mac Nurseries and Joseph Gable, Fred Lee, Tony Shammarello, Bellingrath Gardens, B. Y. Morrison, Neil W. Stuart, and Sam Ensweller. Kenneth McDonald served as the chairman of the Virginia Nurserymen Association Committee concerning Azalea Flower Spot Disease control in the late 1940's.
All newsletters have been removed from this collection and placed in the open accession 10,553-c.
Organization
These records are arranged into four series, with individual folders in alphabetical order within each series: 1) American Rhododendron Society Records (Boxes 1-7); 2) American Rhododendron Society Bound Volumes (Boxes 8-9); 3) Middle Atlantic Chapter Records (Boxes 10-12); 4) Le-Mac Nurseries Records (Box 12).
Container List
- Series I: America Rhododendron Society Records
  - American Horticultural Society, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Awards Committee, 1954-1976 & 1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Bills Paid, 1960-1971 (Box Box 1)
  - Birmingham Chapter, 1969-1970 (Box Box 1)
  - Chapter Correspondence & Related Material, 1955-1987 & n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Chapter Information, 1964-1971 (Box Box 2)
  - Chapter President and Secretary Lists, 1967-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - Clarke, Dr. J. Harold, 1960-1969; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Committees, 1969 & 1973-1974 (Box Box 2)
  - Controversy re Transfer of Research & Education Funds to the Research Foundation Account, 1982-1983 (Box Box 2)
  - Coosa Chapter Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence - A-Z, 1959-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Dunn, Edward B.- Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box Box 2)
  - Elections, 1963-1980 & 1986 (Box Box 2)
  - Financial Statements & Audit Reports, 1948-1959 (Box Box 2)
  - Financial Statements & Audit Reports, 1960-1974 & 1983-1986; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Galle, Fred C.- Correspondence, 1979 (Box Box 3)
  - Hansen, Ruth- Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box Box 3)
  - Insurance Policies, 1962-1971 (Box Box 3)
  - International Rhododendron Conference, Portland, Oregon, 1960-1961 (Box Box 3)
  - Kehr, August- Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box Box 3)
  - Martin, A. S.- Correspondence, 1960-1962 & 1969-1983 (Box Box 3)
  - Membership by Chapters, 1964-1967 & 1974 (Box Box 4)
  - Membership, Non-Chapter, 1967-1969; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Correspondence, 1960-1971; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Minutes of the National Board of Directors' Meetings, 1944-1948 (Box Box 4)
  - Minutes of the National Board of Directors' Meetings, 1949-1986; (8 folders) (Box Box 5 & 5a)
  - Minutes of the National Board of Directors' Meetings, 1987 (Box Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1980 (Box Box 6)
  - National Conventions, 1966-1971 (Box Box 6)
  - National Convention of 1980 (Box Box 6)
  - Pacific Conference of 1970, 1969-1970 (Box Box 6)
  - Phetteplace, Dr. Carl H.- Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box Box 6)
  - Plant Hunting in China - Book Orders, 1969 & 1980 (Box Box 6)
  - Policies of the Board, 1985 (Box Box 6)
  - Pollen Bank, 1980-1983 (Box Box 6)
  - Printed Material, 1954-1981 & n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Publication Committee, 1961-1977 & n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Pukeiti Rhododendron Trust, 1967-1969 (Box Box 6)
  - Quarterly Bulletin, 1968-1974 (Box Box 6)
  - Registrar, 1979-1981 (Box Box 7)
  - Rhododendron Rating Project, 1965-1970 (Box Box 7)
  - Rhododendron Species Glossary (Box Box 7)
  - Ring, George W. III- Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box Box 7)
  - Seed Exchange, 1969-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - Show Records, 1946-1950 (Box Box 7)
  - Taxes, 1945, 1950-1952 & 1967-1970 (Box Box 7)
  - Test Garden of the American Rhododendron Society, Portland, Oregon, 1950-1954 (Box Box 7)
  - Ticknor, Dr. Robert L.- Correspondence, 1969 & 1974 (Box Box 7)
- Series II: America Rhododendron Society Bound Volumes
  - Advertising Record Book, 1961-1964 (Box Box 8)
  - Financial Record Books, 1944-1961; (6 volumes w/ over-lapping date ranges) (Box Box 8)
  - Financial Record Books, 1959-1970; (2 volumes w/ over-lapping date ranges) (Box Box 9)
  - Membership Record Book, 1947-1951 (Box Box 9)
- Series III: Middle Atlantic Chapter Records
  - Controversy re Transfer of Research & Education Funds to the Research Foundation Account, 1982-1983 (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence of Kenneth McDonald, 1949-1964 & n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 10)
  - Correspondence re the Formation of the Middle Atlantic Chapter, 1952-1953 (Box Box 10)
  - Denmark Chapter Suggestions re Payment of Dues Increases, 1985 (Box Box 10)
  - Gold Medal Nominations, 1981-1983 (Box Box 10)
  - Joint Regional Meeting, 1980 (Box Box 10)
  - Membership, 1976-1980; (2 folders) (Box Box 10)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Newsletter Ideas, 1975-1983 (Box Box 10)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Newsletter Ideas, 1984-1987 (Box Box 11)
  - Political Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box Box 11)
  - Quarterly Bulletin Reviews, 1981-1982 (Box Box 11)
  - Secretary-Treasurer Records, 1975-1977; (4 folders) (Box Box 11)
  - Secretary-Treasurer Records, 1978-1981; (4 folders) (Box Box 12)
- Series IV: Le-Mac Nurseries Records
  - Azalea Flower Spot Disease, 1934-1951; (2 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Correspondence with Joseph Gable, 1931-1955 (Box Box 12)
  - Correspondence with Fred Lee, Tony Shammarello, and Bellingrath Gardens, 1947-1961 (Box Box 12)
  - Correspondence with B. Y. Morrison, Neil W. Stuart, and Sam Ensweller, 1947-1950 (Box Box 12)